Interest rates in China's bond market
are aggressively declining, particularly
at the front end of the yield curve
there. It's a classic bond bull case,
except
like in all other cases, it's not
bullish. The question is, where is this
coming from? Is it coming from inside of
China or looking outside? And to that
end, the Chinese government just did
something that will have you shaking
your head where it comes to consumer
spending data and retail sales. Another
key sign which relates to what's going
on here.
Because that might be a big clue about
where this big move in Chinese bonds is
coming from. The combination of what is
looking more and more like flat beverage
China plus the ongoing fallout from the
energy shock, particularly as it ripples
all throughout Asia and beyond. While
stock markets, as you probably know, are
doing just what we said they would,
reacting to the Iran ceasefire
developments with orgiastic euphoria, do
not overlook these other signals simply
because they're looking past the short
run, unlike equities. There's much more
here than simply an oil price spike,
especially when bold bulls and bonds are
big time bothering Beijing.
The rallying in the short end of the
Chinese curve has continued here in
April despite the ceasefire and
re-risking in other markets. Instead,
the Chinese bond market is saying
not much has changed. Now, the question
we need to ask is whether the bond
market is saying not much has changed
about China or is it saying, which it
often does, there's much more globally
synchronization in the Chinese bond
market than people expect. Is it saying
nothing has changed as far as the global
economic outlook or the global financial
outlook given everything that's happened
over the last several months? So, Steve,
let's talk about China here because the
Chinese bond market is sending a very
important signal that's being lost in
the re-risking across the certainly
stock markets and other markets that are
near you fork for understandable reasons
given the what looks to be an off-ramp
to the rand conflicts, Um,
you know, depending on how that works
out, but
the Chinese bond market's a big one. Not
many people pay attention to it because
I think a lot of people think it's just
about China. It has nothing to do with
the rest of the world. It is far more
integrated and globally synchronized
than people really give it credit for.
>> That's absolutely right, Jeff, because I
mean, they're the world's largest
exporter. So, from the standpoint of if
something is wrong in their country,
it's because something is starting to be
wrong everywhere else, meaning consumers
are pulling back, financial conditions
are starting to tighten. That's exactly
what we're seeing on the front end of
the curve here, is that yes, the Iran
war did cause some issues across the
board, but the reality is China's
economy was already slowing, was already
having issues. I mean, the banks are out
going out buying the long end of the
curve. Meanwhile, Beijing kept telling
them no, you're going to get slaughtered
here when rates go up, but yet the front
end of the curve continues to go down
because while all of this is having an
impact for China's economy, the trend
continues to be lower. Stimulus isn't
working. Nothing seems to be working at
all for them, and that's exactly what
the bond market's trying to say here
because if you think that China's
problem is isolated to China, and I know
a lot of American investors right now,
Jeff, are looking at the S&P and the
Nasdaq at all-time highs and saying,
"Who really cares?" It matters, just not
today.
>> Yeah, well, it matters, I think, in
China. I mean, look, the Chinese have
been buying gold for a long time. In
fact, there's a parallel move there
because it's it's exactly what you said.
If you're in China today, you're looking
around, you're thinking, "What should I
be buying as an investment?" Uh the
Chinese bank said in unequivocal terms,
"We are not lending into the real
economy. We have nothing We have nothing
to do with that. Maybe we'll lend to
some of the state-owned businesses where
we're relatively protected. We think we
have decent collateral." In this case, I
mean, political collateral. But other
than that, they've been buying bonds.
Like you said, Steve, the PBOC in 2024
warned the Chinese banks, "Don't you buy
government bonds because when everything
works and the system picks up again,
those bonds It's going to be like 2023
all over again. You know, rates are
going to fly higher and it's going to
bankrupt you. And the Chinese bank said,
"You have no idea what you're talking
about, Mr. Regulator, because we are
going to continue buying bonds." And
then what do we see in in late 2024?
Bonds Yields just plunged. Now, they
studied in 2025, and that's what brings
us to this this uh the signal that we're
getting here 2026. After studying in
2025, you know, coming off the rate the
low yields from uh 2024 and early 2025,
they studied for a while, but then last
fall started to you know, the bull
steepening came back on the Chinese
curve, and then it really picked up here
in 2026. And for a while there,
certainly in March, you could say,
"Well, that's just the Iran conflict
that's going to have major economic
impact across especially Asia." And as
you said, Steve, China's a big exporter.
A lot of their product goes to the rest
of Asia. In fact, Asia's one of their
biggest marketplaces. So, if if Asia's
going to get stung by the uh Iran
conflict and the oil energy shock, it's
going to hurt China. But, like I said,
the bull steepening has continued here
in April, and it's gotten to the point
where the one-year Chinese bond yield is
down to 1.15%,
which it hasn't been that low since
January of last year at the you know,
the tail end of that flush in rates. So,
we have to again, we have to ask the
question, what is going on here with the
Chinese bond market bull steepening in
really aggressive fashion?
>> And you know what, Jeff, that's really
interesting because you know, I read an
article just not too long ago, and they
said the reason rates in China are going
down is because there's just too much
liquidity in the financial system, and
it needs a home. And I know you love
that because it's absolutely not true.
But, let's just pretend for a moment
maybe it is true. Maybe there is too
much money. Now, why would that happen?
Well, if you look at the PMIs there at
the factory sector, what do we continue
to see? Demand dropping. New orders are
just not there. So, if you're a
business, as you kind of said, there's
you know, you look around, where are you
going to invest? Well, there's nowhere
to go. So, you might as well put
yourself into risk-free Treasuries,
maybe buy some gold, things that are
liquid. So, then you look at the
consumer's perspective. What do we
continue to see with Chinese consumers?
Well, they're not buying a bunch of real
estate anymore because that market has
continued to slide. They're not spending
a ton of money. So, they're worried,
too, because they're looking saying,
"Wow, we go to work and there isn't that
much work. So, what should we do?" Well,
the same thing. We should seek safety
and security. And then, on top of that,
as you said, the banks seeking safety
and security. Of course, it's obvious
why rates are going down. It's because
the Chinese economy is going down.
>> Yeah, there's too much liquid I love
that. I mean, yes, there is. There's too
much liquidity for safe instruments,
which is always the signal. That's the
part people don't get. Yeah, there's too
much money chasing too few safe
instruments, which is a clear signal
that the marketplace doesn't want to
take risk. If there was just too much
general liquidity, then banks would be
lending into the real economy. If
there's just too much money laying
around, you would think, "Oh, things are
going to pick up." I don't want to be
owning a government bond that yields a
you know, one 1.79%
you know, the 10-year Chinese Treasury
is down to below 180 again. You don't
want that. You want to go in the real
economy make double digits on something
that you're reasonably sure is going to
pay off in the future. So, the fact that
you know,
there's too much liquidity in China that
if that was even true, the fact that
it's going toward government bonds is
still the same signal that we've been
talking about. There's too much demand
for safety because there's too much fear
over safety and liquidity for that
matter, too.
So, I think the you know, the Chinese
just reported uh some more statistics on
the real economy. Our GDP beat
expectations, but I mean, I don't know
how many people left realize that you
don't take GDP seriously. It's almost
like the establishment survey in the US.
You don't really take the initial
payroll numbers that all that seriously
because of all their various flaws. GDP
in China is another one. You don't
really pay too much attention to it.
Instead, you look at some of the monthly
numbers. Industrial production remains
relatively steady simply because the
Chinese have been able to just make
stuff and ship it everywhere else around
the world except the United States.
They're no longer shipping directly to
the US, but they're exporting around the
rest of the world. And so, the
industrial part of the Chinese economy
is the one anchor there. However,
internal, you know, retail sales,
Chinese consumers can can sense the
shifting employment conditions, and
therefore retail sales have been
questionable. And then there was some
questions about what the uh the Chinese
government did as far as the retail
sales data last month. They did major
revisions. Retail sales had fallen off
pretty sharply to, you know, go
sideways, which is a contraction. But
they had fallen off sharply last year.
And then last month, just clear out of
nowhere, they decided, "Oh, retail sales
didn't fall off sharply. In fact, retail
sales are relatively steady." And then
this month they said,
"No, retail sales did fall off sharply."
And they went right back to where it had
been, you know, the previous month. And
so, you have to wonder what's going on
there. I think it has to do with the
Chinese National Party Congress last
month, not look not wanting to look not
wanting to make the internal retail
sales consumer spending aspect of the
economy look too bad. And then after
that was over, they're like, "Okay,
we're going to go right back to where it
was." But either way, the point stands.
What What Steve just said is that the
Chinese economy is a mess, and it's a
mess that they can only cover up for a
month, apparently, but it's getting
worse, not better. And then you add to
that the possible headwinds from the
energy shock fallout, which is going to
continue to pile up. Uh even if the Iran
conflict is over, as of right now, like
the stock market seems to believe,
there's still going to be economic
consequences, particularly in Asia. And
that's going to add even more headwinds
to the Chinese system. And then there's
other things, too, right, Steve? Um the
Chinese are running into political
interference or political backlash in
places like Europe. I mean, the
Europeans just imposed a 50% tariff on
steel imports from the rest of the
world, wink wink, talking China.
Um so, the Chinese export miracle might
be reaching its end, which would be
another reason for the Chinese banking
sector, and in particular, to start uh
to continue to own safe instruments
because if the export boom suddenly does
uh reverse, that's going to leave China
even more exposed.
>> And Jeff, you're right. It seems like
the export boom is likely to reverse. I
mean, let's take a look at what happened
here in the US. Obviously, consumers are
getting a little bit larger tax-free Not
the 30% everyone was hoping, but it
looks like a few hundred bucks. And what
do we see? They're front-running the
tariffs. You know, or not tariffs, but
the you know, the rising energy prices.
Probably the same thing's happening in
Europe, but we didn't see it happen in
China. So, of course, you've got to
cover this thing up because you don't
want to look and say, "Wow, everybody
else is picking up demand. They're
outspending money. They're buying and
us, we're continuing to slow down." So,
yeah, there's a lot of risk here because
China, you know, they can just crank
stuff out of their factories like nobody
can believe. The problem is the rest of
the world's got to absorb it. And right
now, the rest of the world's saying,
"Look, we don't want your stuff because
our economy is slowing, too. Our workers
are hitting the unemployment line, and
we know that you can come in and
undercut them with steel, with
automobiles, with anything. And we can't
have that because you you look at
Europe. Their economy is likely to go
into a recession here. You see China
likely to go or if not already in a
recession. So, the risks are pretty high
here, and nobody wants to go out and
raise their hand and say, "Hey, we're
first." Because what's going to happen
then? All the people that are chasing
the US equity market higher are going to
turn around and say, "Let's short the
Chinese stock market." And then next
thing you know, everything starts to
come unglued, and they really don't want
that. They're hoping that this
excitement and enthusiasm that's driving
US equity prices higher is going to show
up in China, drive stocks up, get
consumers excited, get them spending,
and get the sad factory sector revived.
But the problem is as we started the
show with and you said, "The bond
market's saying none of that's likely to
happen."
>> In a world where markets swing on every
headline, focus matters. That's why
Eurodollar University offers its one big
weekly theme, a disciplined thematic
analysis that you can count on.
If you don't have time to go all the way
to the depth of Eurodollar University's
comprehensive deep dive analysis, but
you want to get the next best thing, one
big weekly theme is for you.
Each week, we pick the one high-impact
macro and market theme and we unpack it
from first principles, from fundamentals
to real-world implications, so you can
see the forest and the trees, drawing
from all over the vast Eurodollar
University library and canon. What you
get with one big weekly theme is a
single focused theme each week unpacked
with clarity from sources you will not
see anywhere else. Data-driven analysis
supported by charts and information
pulled from Eurodollar University's
other subscriptions and offerings, all
in a simple, repeatable framework you'll
use week after week.
We distill the complexity into a
practical fundamentals-first playbook
that you can rely on. This is not about
chasing every hot idea. It's about
building a disciplined routine that
sharpens your judgment during these
periods of uncertainty. So, if you're
ready to make your week count, subscribe
to one big weekly theme today. Visit
eurodollaruniversity.substack.com
or click the link in the description to
learn more. You can sample the service
or sign up and get started straight
away.
Eurodollar University, a focused
approach to mastering money and macro
one thoughtful week at a time.
>> Yeah, that's the point is that any
positive outcomes here or off-ramps as
far as China's concerned, therefore the
global economy, not not showing up in
Chinese bond market and that's the
signal. You would think if there was
some positive result here, at at a
positive path forward, a recovery path,
which everybody's been looking for,
especially after last year, it would
show up here. Because like I said, the
Chinese bond market has is basically the
best unfiltered view of where the bond
market is globally. And with it bull
steepening, and bull steepening is
simply a case where rates are going
down, but going down more so at the
front end. Let's be clear, the back end
rates are going down, too. Like I said,
the 10-year's below 1.8%, which is
lowest it's been in several months. But
it's really the front end of the curve,
which is saying, "We do not like the
direction the global economy and China's
place within it. We don't like the
direction it's taking." Um you mentioned
unemployment. That was another statistic
that came out this week, too. In
addition to the relatively weird and
grim retail sales numbers, Chinese
unemployment actually picked up by a
tenth, which does not sound like a lot.
It's not a high rate of unemployment,
but in March, which is the month
following the spring festival, the
holiday, usually you see unemployment
rise during the holiday and then fall
afterward. In this case, it didn't.
Unemployment actually went up a little
bit during the holiday, and then in here
in March, uh the latest data we have, it
went up again. Went up a little bit
further. So, it suggests that
potentially, I mean, just one month, you
don't want to make too much out of it.
But when you combine that with the bond
market signal, the grim statistics in
consumer spending, which is Consumers
are saying, "We don't want to spend
because we're afraid of our jobs." Same
as we have over here. You know, it's the
flat beverage environment over here. So,
you see a little bit of a pick up in
unemployment, um some negative signals
out of the economy, the banking sector
that is just pulling back all over the
place.
Now, you start to put You starts to
piece together all of these various
pieces. You put them together, and it
looks like it's the bull steepening that
you would expect.
>> Yeah, and Jeff, and this comes back to
the excess liquidity in the financial
system kind of notion is, "Well, sure,
you know, you have the holiday. What do
you think? Consumers are going to come
out and spend, right? Because maybe
things are going to be on sale.
Businesses have inventory they want to
move. And then maybe there's just so
much sales going on the businesses start
to get optimistic. Maybe they need to
hire some people with some orders. What
did we see? That didn't happen at all.
So again from the household level it
kind of makes it perfect sense what
we're seeing in the bond market is
everybody saying consumers, businesses,
and banks is we don't see any
opportunity in the Chinese economy. We
don't see it turning around. In fact, we
look out in the future and we see
nothing and that's again why long rates
are slowly coming down because as we
know their growth and inflation
expectations. So front end of the curve
telling us financial conditions are
tightening, long end of the curve
telling us that yeah, this thing isn't
turning around and consumers are saying
I don't want to lose my money here. I'm
going to go and buy again as you said
low yielding government bonds because
it's safe and secure.
>> Yeah, it's the banks too. I mean that's
the big the financial firms. What
they're saying is look, um
you know, profitability among Chinese
banks has been squeezed for years. I
mean with interest rates going lower I
get interest Lower interest rates are
not stimulus. Um we always we're always
taught that they are because we take the
perspective or you're you're told to
take the perspective of a borrower. And
so it sounds like okay, lower rates is
cheaper to borrow. I'm going to borrow
more. But nobody ever stops and thinks
about the lenders' perspective. What do
lower rates do to lenders? They squeeze
the profitability. Yes, you can say
well, short-term rates go down and
therefore their lending their their own
borrowing costs their own funding costs
go down.
But that's not really how it works
either. So you've got interest rates
that are going down and Chinese bank
profitability is all but disappeared. In
fact, there's many reports we don't have
a whole lot of great information, but
there are many reports that Chinese
banks, the biggest ones are cash flow
negative. They're burning cash cuz they
have no profitability. They have all of
these foreclosed properties that are,
you know, they need maintenance. They
need tax payments. They need, you know,
if you're going to rent them out, if
you're going to become a landlord, you
can't sell the things. They don't sell
at auctions. So they're bleeding cash.
And so what do the Chinese banks do? You
would think if things were really
picking up, if there was money around
China, you'd be like, "I we need to go
reach for some yield somewhere."
Instead, the banks are saying, "No.
Um the Chinese government bonds are
yielding 1% at the front end. We're
going to buy even more of those." Which
is another again commentary on the
economic situation. So, if you got
rising unemployment, you've got threats
to the export sector, Chinese banks who
have made loans to the real economy cuz
they're often made to make loans to the
real economy, they're even more exposed
to that than they are to the real estate
bust, which is still a big problem
there. Uh the bull steepening signal is
basically, I think, the bond market in
China saying, "Look, we know the
internal situation's bad. We know the
real estate bust that's still going to
happen. What we're now afraid of is the
other part of it. The export boom,
something starts to threaten and pull
back on the uh the uh ability of the
Chinese to send their product around the
rest of the world. I mean, is it the
Iran fallout? Are we going to see a real
demand destruction across Asia where
China wants to send its excess
production to places like, you know,
Vietnam and Malaysia and other parts of
of Asia, Australia? But they simply
can't because there's no demand in those
places because uh they've been paying
too much for oil and energy and
everything else. Is it Europe? Are the
Europeans going to erect um trade
barriers? Is it going to be trade war
three with the Europeans? Um that's what
the the bond market is saying. Yes, we
know China's a mess internally, but
we're now seeing all these threats
emerge externally that just
pile on, pile on, and pile on.
>> Yeah, Jeff, and I completely agree with
that because what is probably the
biggest factor here? You mean, we can
look at the US, perfect example. We saw
energy prices go up, and what did
consumers do? They grabbed their tax
refund checks, and they went out and
bought stuff because they knew, and
we've seen this with the tariffs and
all, you know, going back to COVID. Hey,
prices go up, and you better buy now.
So, they did. So, you think about what
China's bond market is clearly saying
is, "Look, we know there's a lot of
spending going on in other parts of the
world. Not here, but we can see it. But
we know that that's spending is not
going to last because if it did, it we
would become the beneficiaries of it as
our factory sector revived. So, it's
almost very clearly telling the world is
we know this is a short-term move here
in the markets as consumers are
front-running this. Once their stimulus
checks or their tax refund checks kind
of dry up, their spending is going to go
and our bond market is saying this is
the outcome. Now, does it happen in a
month or two? I don't know exactly when
it's going to happen, Jeff. But my
perspective is that's what the Chinese
bond market is saying is if you think
this US stock market hitting all-time
highs means the spending is just going
to ramp up over the next couple months
and that you're going to see the US
economy just roaring to a massive bull
market, yeah, ain't going to happen.
>> Yeah, there's going to be follow. It's
not going to just be immediate stuff,
you know, energy prices go up and then
they come back down and then it's oh, no
big deal, nothing happened. I was the
Qatari finance minister who just a
couple days ago, I think he was at the
IMF meeting in Washington said,
"You're going to see the real stuff hit
in a couple months."
Um, first of all, there's a lot of a lot
of this damaged infrastructure in in
across the Middle East to begin with,
but just beyond that, things that have
already happened over the last 6 weeks,
7 weeks now since the conflict began,
have really, you know, they've really
scrambled the global system to quite an
extent. It's going to take a little
while to get through. And let's be let's
face it, the global system was not in
good shape to begin with, so you throw a
little bit of that on top of everything
else. It was a fragile situation I think
that's what the Chinese bond market is
saying is looking past the current
energy spike. It's not about the price
of oil any longer, it's about what
happened when oil prices were spiking
that led to second, third, and even
fourth-order effects that we aren't even
imagining yet. You know, we talked last
week, Steve, about food and fertilizer.
That's a longer-term thing that's going
to show up in a couple months.
So, that's what I think the bond market
signal here is yes, China's a mess, it's
not turning around, but now we're seeing
you know the one thing about China that
was working was its ability to export to
the rest of the world. Now we're saying,
oh crap, now maybe something happened to
that. So that's the signal here. Chinese
bull steepening is a big deal and it's
one that is getting lost. I mean first
of all it's Chinese bond market, who
pays attention to that? And it's really
getting lost under the signal of hey,
stocks are soaring, all time highs, who
cares about anything else? Um
this is one you definitely need to care
about.